developer sooner or later you are going
to be asked to implement a feature that
most web applications need infinite
scrolling infinite scrolling is what
websites like Twitter Tick Tock Facebook
and YouTube all have they detect when
you are about to reach the end of the
page and quickly load and add more posts
to the end of the page to give you the
illusion that you can scroll forever
this video isn't specifically about
infinite scrolling this video is about
the API that makes it incredibly easy to
implement the intersection of server API
the intersection of server API will
watch an element and let us know when
that element is visible to the user
that's it so let's see how it works here
we have a scroll level page that has a
circle at the end of it using the
intersection of server API we will
detect when the circle is visible to the
user so we can run some custom code and
perform some animations for example the
HTML of the page is very simple all we
have is an empty div with a circle ID
and the JavaScript side is where the
magic happens first we are grabbing the
circle then we are creating a new
intersection of server and finally we
are telling the Observer to observe the
circle element if we save this code and
load our page we're going to get an
error the reason why is because if we
think about it our code is just
observing the circle but we don't want
to only observe the circle we want to
also be notified when the circle enters
or exits the screen of the user that is
why when we create an intersection
Observer we must give it a function that
will be called when an element enters or
exits the screen of the user we will put
that function as the first argument of
the intersection of server Constructor
and as you can see the function receives
the items that entered or exit the
screen on the first parameter which for
now we are just going to console log
when we refresh the page and open the
console we will immediately see an array
of intersection of server entry appear
an intersection of server entry is
information about the elements that we
are watching that entered or left the
screen of the user if we open that array
and look at the first item we will see
an object like this here we have
information about the Target and
intersection like the bounding client
ranked object that gives us the X and Y
coordinates and size of the Target in
this case the circle or the intersection
red object that gives us the X and Y
coordinates and size of only the visible
area of the target the one we care about
is the is intersecting property this
tells us if the circle is visible on the
screen or not as you can see is
intersecting is initially false since
the circle isn't on the screen now we
are going to slowly scroll down the page
and the moment the server call starts to
be a little bit visible we will see
another array in our console containing
one item our Circle but this time with
the property is intersecting set to true
to make our life easier we will change
the code a little bit here all we are
doing is going through each item of the
list of items we are checking if they
are visible if they are we are console
logging the element and the text is
visible here is where if you are
building an infinite scrolling you will
call your API to get more posts our
console now looks like this as you can
see the intersection Observer is very
exact I say that because if we scroll
down the page slowly the moment just a
tiny pixel of the circle comes into the
screen the intersection Observer will
run our code and tell us the circle is
visible to configure our intersection
Observer to wait until at least a half
of the circle is invisible to fire our
code we can change our code to look like
this on the second argument of the
intersection of server Constructor we
can pass some options and one of them is
threshold threshold is a number between
0 and 1. the default is zero which means
that as soon as one pixel of the circle
is visible we will be notified if we
change it to 0.5 that means that only
when 50 of our circle is visible then we
will be notified if we set it to 1 it
would mean waiting for a hundred percent
of the circle to be visible for the code
to fire as you can see it works like a
charm and we now have to scroll until
more than half of the circle for our
code to Fire and that's it those are the
basics of intersection Observer it is
now our job to combine this API with CSS
classes to build something awesome like
this for example whereas we scroll up
and down the elements in our list appear
from from the bottom and disappear at
the top with a beautiful animation that
effect is easy to accomplish here is the
HTML on the CSS each div is a square
with a background color a border and a
border radius each div by default has an
opacity of zero and it is transformed to
make it look a little bit big then we
have a class called visible this class
will scale our Square to normal size and
give it an opacity of one on our
JavaScript we are grabbing all the
squares then we are creating an
intersection of server and we are
checking if the square is visible on the
screen or not if it is we are adding the
visible class and if it isn't we are
removing it it is just a game of adding
and removing class names and that's it
for this video I hope you found it
useful and I hope you learned something
new if you did like this video And
subscribe to the channel and before I go
I wanted to let you know that we have
launched a new community program called
the 10-week study it is a program where
instead of studying alone and giving up
in the middle we have daily code
challenges and quizzes to practice what
we learn and we do it all together we
have a Discord server weekly online
calls and we also meet offline to play
some games and have pizza and beer right
now registration is open for two
programs one is the web 10-week study
that is for absolute beginners where we
learn HTML CSS JavaScript node.js
Express and mongodb and number two is
the flutter 10 weeks study where we will
learn dark flutter flutter animations in
Firebase by building seven different
mobile apps click the link below to
learn more details on how to join
see you on the next one bye
[Music]